I've received many such comments in the comment section.
I've also heard
that when a customer
applies for a home loan at a bank, they are
told they must also
take out a life insurance policy. This is a
guideline issued by the RBI. Secondly, the
RBI has only issued guidelines
that banks should educate their customers on the
importance of life insurance and
explain why they should
take out a life insurance policy with their loan. However, this does
not mean that
you must also take out a life insurance
policy with your home loan. Name: Pankaj Mathpal,
Certified Financial Planner. In today's
video, we'll discuss
how important it is to
take out a life insurance policy with your loan, and if you do,
what kind of policy should you choose.
When banks offer you a loan, they say they're
insuring your loan.
Friends, insurance isn't for the loan itself; it's for the
person taking the loan. The
purpose is to insure the life insurance policy
if the borrower dies during the loan term.
In that case, the bank should not face any problem in recovering its money
and for this, they advise
that whoever is eligible should get his insurance done.
Friends, when a person takes a home loan for 10 years, 15 years or
20 years, then in such a situation,
if that person dies, then the
family members may face difficulty in paying the EMI or
in repairing the amount that is acquired. Accordingly, when
a loan is taken, especially a home loan, then
taking a term life insurance policy is
a good option. If you have an
oil
grade 1 term insurance plan with add-on death benefit, then you do
not need to take a separate policy.
Or if you say that you would like to take
a term insurance plan from outside as per your requirement, then
friends, this may also be
good for you. If the bank from which you are
taking the loan has a
tie-up with a life insurance company, if you
want to take a life insurance policy from that company also, then there is no
harm in it, but
before taking the policy, before signing the proposal form,
definitely check its premium.  If
you buy
a term insurance plan with the same features and same day benefits from
another life insurance company, then it is
possible that your premium may be
lower than the policy you are talking to the bank about.
Apart from this, if you have decided that
you would like to buy a term insurance plan from the bank itself, then it is better for
you
not to take a single premium policy at all.
Instead, you should opt for a regular premium policy.
What happens in a single premium policy is
that you pay the entire premium at once.
Suppose your loan
amount is high, then the bank gives you
a life insurance policy with 2 years' salary
and takes its premium together
in a single premium. Now
what they do with this single premium is that they
add it to your loan amount. Then the
bank will tell you that you do
not have to pay it separately, it will be deducted from your loan.
So friends, on one hand you have taken a loan,
suppose you take a loan of Rs 50 lakh and
you are buying a life insurance policy with a death benefit of Rs 50 lakh, so let's say
its premium
comes to Rs 1.5 lakh in single premium. So, on the one
hand,  You have taken a loan of Rs 50 lakh and you have to
pay interest on it this May and along with that,
you will keep paying interest every year on the life insurance premium that the bank has added to your loan.
So if your premium is
Rs 1.5 lakh, it will increase further after adding interest.
Instead, if you
take a regular premium and pay it off, then perhaps you too can do it in this way
and it is very important that if you have taken a loan of Rs 10 lakh, then
along with it, you have a life insurance
policy, that too has been made zero,
but suppose you complete it after 10 years, in
such a case, it will remain dormant and
you will want to surrender it saying that
you do not need it, then in that case,
either you will get a little premium back
or it is possible that
according to the terms and conditions of the policy, you may
not get any premium back and your policy may
not be surrendered at all. In such a situation, if you
take a policy with regular premium, then the choice is
in your hands that now you can
stop paying the premium whenever you want and the terms
of your policy will start again.
Friends, if you want to take a life insurance policy, then the
term will start from this.  You
may need an insurance policy, but keep in
mind that you should compare the premiums of the policies in the market and then only choose
a term
insurance policy as per your need and also a
single premium policy and if you are
taking a single premium policy then also
you should not add it to your loan, you should
not need to take a loan on a spontaneity,
you also have money, only then you can buy it, well even if you have
money because you are
taking a policy with less money at this time, but as far as
possible you should take a policy with regular premium,
how did you like the information, do
tell me by commenting in the comment box and also do
not forget to like this video and friends,
share this video as much as possible
and if you have not yet subscribed to our YouTube channel, then
subscribe to it and also paste the bell icon and
press the answer, then
whenever a new video plays, you
get its notification,
due to which you get that information immediately, we will
meet you again with similar important information, thank you, Jai Hind